Deans, Marie; Papers apap377
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Marie Deans Papers
1957-2015
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap377
4.36 cubic ft.
This collection documents the death penalty abolitionist work of Marie McFadden Deans. A smaller amount of personal materials, such as Deans' poetry and writing, also is included.
Content Description
This collection includes writings, papers, newsclips, publications, business and personal correspondence, reports, subject files, court documents, legal case work, organizational documents, poetry, short stories, and photographs saved by, created by, and/or related to Marie Deans and her anti-death penalty work from 1957 to 2015. Not all folder dates are inclusive.
Materials from the Virginia Coalition on Jails and Prisons (VCJP), spanning from 1983 when it was founded by Deans up until its closure in 1993, are featured. This includes reports, projects, correspondence, flyers, press releases, letters, and memos to attorneys from Deans' time with VCJP. Materials from Deans' work with Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation (MVFR) can also be found in this collection. MVFR newsletters, board correspondence, conference information, fundraising, minutes, and articles about and by members of MVFR stretching into the early 2000s illustrate Deans' undying passion for anti-death penalty activism. Photographs of incarcerated individuals, correctional facilities, Death Row, activism, and Marie Deans are a highlight of the collection. Additionally, personal correspondence between Deans and individuals facing the death penalty or their family members provides unique insight into the lives of those on Death Row. An abundance of news clippings that Deans kept documenting the death penalty, Death Row, cases Deans worked on, VCJP, Mecklenburg Correctional Center, and executions from the 1980s to early 2000s are present.
Biographical Note
Marie McFadden Deans (1940-2011) was a death penalty abolitionist and mitigation specialist who advocated for individuals on Death Row. Following the murder of her mother-in-law Penny Deans in 1972, Marie Deans began to voice her opposition to capital punishment. In 1976, Marie Deans formed Murder Victims' Families Against the Death Penalty (later called Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation), an organization for those whose loved ones had been killed by someone and oppose the death penalty. From 1978 to 1981, Deans served on the National Death Penalty Committee for the Charleston chapter of Amnesty International (of which Deans founded) to investigate Death Row and clemency procedures. After moving to Virginia from South Carolina in 1983, she established the Virginia Coalition on Jails and Prisons (VCJP), serving as Executive Director to this organization dedicated to recruiting and assisting lawyers for death penalty appeals, abolishing the death penalty, and promoting clemency in Virginia and beyond. Additionally, Deans worked with other organizations such as the South Carolina Coalition Against the Death Penalty, Southern Coalition on Jails and Prisons, and Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty.
Deans worked on legal cases – those of individuals already on Death Row and individuals on trial for capital crimes, hoping to mitigate their sentences and ensure post-conviction counsel. The cases of Earl Washington, Jr. (exonerated in 2000) and Joe Giarratano (death sentence commuted in 1991) are two of Deans' more high-profile success stories on Death Row. Deans was present for the executions of almost three dozen individuals and regularly visited inmates on Death Row in Virginia and South Carolina. Deans wrote articles, short stories, and books about her work hoping to raise public awareness of Death Row procedures and cases.
Although the Virginia Coalition on Jails and Prisons closed in 1993 due to a lack of funding, Deans continued to investigate cases, find inmates attorneys, petition for clemency, call for the abolishment of the death penalty, and advocate for prisoners until her death from lung cancer.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order. There are no series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Robert Deans, son of Marie Deans, donated all materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2018.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted except for one folder noted on the finding aid.
Deans, Marie McFadden, 1940-2011; Death Penalty; Capital punishment--United States.; Capital punishment--Virginia; Death row inmates.; Virginia Coalition on Jails and Prisons; Murder victims' families; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Clippings, newspaper; Files by subject; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records)
- 1985 Death Row Escape Attempt (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1992 Program Report of the Virginia Coalition on Jails and Prisons, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1993 Monthly Monitor (Box 1, Folder 3)
- ACLU Correspondence, 1990; 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Amicus Brief (Huertas), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Amnesty International, 1979-1983; 1985-1987; 1989; 1992-1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Book Business, 1994; 1996; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Business Correspondence, 1996-1997; 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Capital Punishment/ Lutheran Church, 1978-1979; 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Case in Mitigation, 1992; 2002-2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Cases/ Law, 1990; 1998-2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Checklists for Records, 1990-1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Chevis Clark: A Profile by Marie Deans, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Clemency, 1990-1991; 2004; 2008-2009; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Clippings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Coleman Leake Johnson, 1990; 1992-1993; 1996-1997; 2000-2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Congratulations to Joe Giarratano, 1982; 1991; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence- Mike, Larry, Doug, Carol, 1981-1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence with Joe, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Deans, Amnesty International, 1979-1983; 1985; 1987; 1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Deans, Articles/ Drafts (1 of 2), 1975; 1978-1980; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Deans, Articles/ Drafts (2 of 2), 1975; 1978-1980; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Deans, Articles Ideas, 1982-1983; 1986; 1989; 1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Deans, Articles/ Unpublished, 1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Deans, Book/ II, 2003-2004; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Deans, Book/ Drafts, 1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Deans, Book/ Editing, 1999; 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Deans, Book/ Joe Giarratano Dropping Appeals Chapter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Deans, Book Proposal, 2002-2005; Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Deans, Book, Ricky Chapter, 1988; 2002-2003; 2006; 2015; Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Deans, Correspondence to and About, 1981-2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Deans, Correspondence with S.C. Officials, 1980-1981; 1983; 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Deans, Correspondence with Victim Families, 1981-1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Deans, Death Penalty Articles, 1977; 1987; Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Deans, Interviews, 1981; 1988; 2005-2006; Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Deans, Notebook Thoughts No. 1, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Deans, Notebook Thoughts No. 2, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Deans, Notebook Thoughts No. 3, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Deans, Notebook Thoughts No. 4, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Deans, Poetry, 1982; 1984; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Deans, Speeches, 1986-1987; 1991-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Deans, Stories, Published, 1972; 1976-1977; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Deans, Stories, Unfinished/Unpublished, 1979-1980; 1983; 1985-1986; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Deans, Story Fragments, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Deans, Unidentified Correspondence, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Death House, 1987; 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Death Penalty, 04/18/85 Riot at State Penitentiary (J.B. Briley), 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Death Penalty, Botched Executions, 1982-1983; 1990; Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Death Penalty, Correspondence, Lobbying Churches, 1985; 1990; 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Death Penalty, Evans v. Muncy, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Death Penalty, Executions/ Charlie Brooks, 1977; 1980-1984; 2003; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Death Penalty, Executions/ History, 1985; 1990; Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Death Penalty, Executions/ Linwood Briley, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Death Penalty, Executions/ Michael Smith, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Death Penalty, Executions/ Terry Roach, 1985-1986; Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Death Penalty, Executions/ Witnesses, 1984; 1987; 1994 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Death Penalty, Expansion in Virginia, 1991; 1998 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Death Penalty, History of the Resource Center, 1986-1988; 1990-1991; Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Death Penalty, Juveniles, 1986; 1991; Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Death Penalty, Lawyers for Death Row, 1984-1986; 1988; 1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Death Penalty, Poll, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Death Row Virginia, 1986; 1988; 1992-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Death Watch, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Debate, Rose- Columbia and Charleston, 1980-1981; 1984; Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- DOC Experts' Involvement in Killing Richard Whitley, 1987; Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Earl Washington, Jr., 1977-2003; Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Earl Washington, Jr.: An Innocent Man (1 of 2), 1967-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Earl Washington, Jr.: An Innocent Man (2 of 2), 1967-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Electric Chair Examination, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Executions, Effect on Corrections Officers and Administrators, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Experts, 1984-2004; Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
- History of Death Penalty in Virginia, 1985-1987; 1992-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Joe Giarratano, 1984-2000; Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Joe Savino, 1990-1991; Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Marie Deans Bibliography, Undated (Floppy-disk 1)
- Marie Deans: In Memoriam, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Marie Deans Introduction, Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Marie Deans: The Bibliography, 1980-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Marie, Miscellaneous Readings, 1957-2015; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Mecklenburg Correctional Center, 1984 Death Row Escape, 1989; 2004 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Mecklenburg Correctional Center, 1984 Wiretap, 1981; 1985; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Mecklenburg Correctional Center, July 26, 1984, 1984-1985; Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Meeting with Death Row, 12/30/1983, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Memorandum Agreement, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Mitigation- About, 1987; 2000-2003; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Mitigation: A Last Chance at Life, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Motion for Appointment, 2002; Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- MVFR, Articles About Members, 1986-1987; 1989; 1991-2000; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- MVFR, Articles by Members, 1984; 1987-1989; 1993-1996; 1999; Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- MVFR, Board Correspondence, 1989-1997; 1999; Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- MVFR, Conference, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- MVFR, Deans, 1993-2007; Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- MVFR, Fundraising, 1994-2000; Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- MVFR, Minutes, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- MVFR, Newsletters, 1991-1992; 1994-1995; 1997-2000; 2006 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- MVFR, Virginia Chapter, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- My Three Hours on Death Row by Frank Jones, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Newsclips, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Newsclips, 1983: January-June, 1983 January-1983 June (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Newsclips, 1983: July-December, 1983 July-1983 December (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Newsclips, 1984: January-March, 1984 January-1984 March (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Newsclips, 1984: April-June, 1984 April-1984 June (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Newsclips, 1984: August-December, 1984 August-1984 December (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Newsclips, 1985: March-June, 1985 March-1985 June (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Newsclips, 1985: July-September, 1985 July-1985 September (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Newsclips, 1985: October (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Newsclips, 1986: January-March, 1986 January-1986 March (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Newsclips, 1986: June-August, 1986 June-1986 August (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Newsclips, 1986: October-December, 1986 October-1986 December (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Newsclips, 1987: January-March, 1987 January-1987 March (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Newsclips, 1987: April-June, 1987 April-1987 June (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Newsclips, 1987: July-September, 1987 July-1987 September (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Newsclips, 1987: October-December, 1987 October-1987 December (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Newsclips, 1988: January-March, 1988 January-1988 March (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Newsclips, 1988: April-December, 1988 April-1988 December (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Newsclips, 1989: January-March, 1989 January-1989 March (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Newsclips, 1989: April-June, 1989 April-1989 June (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Newsclips, 1989: July-September, 1989 July-1989 September (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Newsclips, 1989: October-December, 1989 October-1989 December (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Newsclips, 1990: January-March, 1990 January-1990 March (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Newsclips, 1990: April-June, 1990 April-1990 June (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Newsclips, 1990: July-September, 1990 July-1990 September (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Newsclips, 1990: October-December, 1990 October-1990 December (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Newsclips, 1991: January-March, 1991 January-1991 March (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Newsclips, 1991: April-June, 1991 April-1991 June (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Newsclips, 1991: July-September, 1991 July-1991 September (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Newsclips, 1991: October-December, 1991 October-1991 December (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Newsclips, 1992: January-March, 1992 January-1992 March (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Newsclips, 1992; April-June, 1992 April-1992 June (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Newsclips, 1992: July-September, 1992 July-1992 September (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Newsclips, 1992: October-December, 1992 October-1992 December (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Newsclips, 1993: January-March, 1993 January-1993 March (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Newsclips, 1993: April-June, 1993 April-1993 June (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Newsclips, 1993: July-September, 1993 July-1993 September (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Newsclips, 1993: October-December, 1993 October-1993 December (Box 3, Folder 58)
- Newsclips, 1994: January-March, 1994 January-1994 March (Box 3, Folder 59)
- Newsclips, 1994: July-September, 1994 July-1994 September (Box 3, Folder 60)
- Newsclips, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Newsclips, 1997: October-December, 1997 October-1997 December (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Newclips, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Newsclips, 2001: January-March, 2001 January-2001 March (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Photograph, Baydar, Undated (Flat-file 1)
- Photographs and Correspondence, Death Row and Visiting Area of the Death House, 2003; Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Photographs, Correctional Facilities, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Photographs, Identified Incarcerated Individuals, Dated, 1978; 1984-1988; 1990; 1993; 1999 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Photographs, Identified Incarcerated Individuals, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Photographs, Joe Giarratano, 1991; Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Photographs, Marie Deans, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photographs, Marie Deans and Activism, Dated, 1989-1990; 1992; 1996; 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Photographs, Unidentified Incarcerated Individuals, Dated, 1982-1986; 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Photographs, Unidentified Incarcerated Individuals, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Photographs, Unidentified Persons, 1991; Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Pre-Trial Tracking and Assistance Project, 1987; 1989 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Prisons, Mecklenburg Correctional Center, General, 1981-1987; 1990-1992; Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Protest Signs Sent to Marie, 1992 (Flat-file 2)
- Ramey Case, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Review of Virginia's System of Capital Punishment, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Roger Keith Coleman (1 of 2), 1984; 1988; 1990-1992; 2006; Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Roger Keith Coleman (2 of 2), 1984; 1988; 1990-1992; 2006; Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Sosnowski Pofile, 1977; Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
- South Carolina, 1980-1981; 1983-1987; Undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Southern Coalition on Jails and Prisons, Comedy Night Poster, Undated (Flat-file 3)
- Telephone Calls, 1986 April 2-1986 June 19 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Telephone Calls, Loose Paper, 1985; Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Telephone Calls, Steno Book, Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- They Fought for the Life of Earl Washington Jr. and Won, 2004 (Video-tape 1)
- Unidentified Office Procedure, 1967 June 15 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- United Kingdom Documentary, "First Tuesday" Donations - RESTRICTED, 1986-1987; 2005 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Please consult an archivist to view.
- VCJP, 1985 Search for Lawyers, Undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
- VCJP, 1992 Program Report, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- VCJP, Access, 1982-1987; 1989-1991; Undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
- VCJP, Flyers, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
- VCJP, Press Releases, 1989-1994; 2005; Undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
- VCJP, Memos to Attorneys, 1983-1989 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Virginia Coalition on Jails and Prisons (1 of 2), 1982-1993; Undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Virginia Coalition on Jails and Prisons (2 of 2), 1982-1993; Undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Virginia Execution News, 1979; 1982; 1985; Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Virginia Jurisdictions Map, Undated (Flat-file 4)
- The Virginian Pilot, 1994 June 26 (Flat-file 5)
- The Virginian Pilot, 1984 September 16 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty, 1999; 2007; Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Writing Criticisms, 1998; 2002; 2005; 2008; Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)